foreign
[Music]
to Nowhere
come on inside
[Music]
taking my ride to nowhere
we'll take that right
I'm feeling okay this morning
and you know
to Paradise
here we go
[Music]
in my mind come along and take that ride
and it's all right baby it's all right
and it's very far away but it's a
growing day by day it's all right baby
it's all right
do you like to come along and you can
help me sing this song and it's all
right
maybe it's all right
there's a city in my mind come along
[Music]
and it's very far away but it's growing
deep out there it's alive baby it's all
right they could tell you what to do but
they'll make
[Music]
foreign
hello everyone thank you so much for
tuning in
um as you guys know I'm kind of a little
excited for tonight's show
um this is so rad and I'm so honored and
excited
um to have Mr John kiriaku
um you are a journalist and author
um and a Former Intelligence officer
um so I know I actually I thought of
this while I was
um prepping
well first let me let me uh why don't
you introduce yourself on a deeper level
than I just
oh thanks there's not much more to say
uh I'm a former CIA officer
um I've sort of become something of a
CIA dissident I suppose
um
my claim to fame is I blew the whistle
on the cia's torture program something
I've never ever regretted doing uh the
price was high but uh but that's okay
glad that I was able to do it and uh and
happy to be with you thanks for the
invitation
absolutely so something I was thinking
about while I was
um you know coming up with my questions
and such it it struck me funny because a
lot of us on Twitter who you know people
disagree with like every time they
disagree with someone they call them an
OP or CIA and I was just wondering if
you've seen that and like is that weird
to you
you know people still call me CIA people
say stupid things like once CIA always
CIA and it's like oh I'll be sure to
mention that to Ed Snowden next time I
talk to him right or or to uh to uh
Jeffrey Sterling or somebody like that
you know it's it's just you get that
nonsense all the time and it's always
from people who just are so
intellectually lazy that they um that
they have nothing else to argue
right absolutely that's exactly what I
say they're lazy absolutely to bring on
the pejoratives I have no uh no
discussion in me
um so I want to kind of give people I'm
sure most of my viewers know at least
somewhat of who you are but I want to
kind of go back
um and actually it's really interesting
um you were actually recommended for the
CIA job through your college professor
in grad school yes he recruited me into
the CIA I was in grad school at George
Washington University
getting a master's degree in legislative
affairs I just
kind of figured that I would end up on
Capitol Hill someday or maybe in the
Foreign Service maybe as a lobbyist and
uh and I was taking this class called
the psychology of leadership by uh
doctor or with Dr Gerald post and
um he was an eminent psychiatrist he
he's he used to be on TV all the time he
had written a dozen books like deep
kinds of books and um
and one day after class it's kind of a
longish story but I'll make it very very
short but one day after class
uh he asked me he has to see me in his
office
when I went down there he told me that
he was not really a professor there he
was a CIA officer undercover as a
professor there and he was looking for
people who might fit into the cia's
culture
and this was on the analytics side he
actually had founded one of the cia's
analytic divisions and would I be
interested in uh in joining the CIA the
truth of the matter is that I was
getting married just six weeks later and
I had no job
and I had no clawspecs for a job and so
I said sure I wanted to see the world
anyway I was interested in public
service I hadn't given it a whole ton of
thought
but I said sure
and uh you know it's not it's not that
simple you have to pass a whole bunch of
tests written oral Financial
polygraph security uh but eventually I
found myself at the CIA
wow so and you
you definitely did work with different
countries so where
do you primarily serve in DC or did you
get to travel
oh the CIA sent me to 70 different
countries and I lived in a half a dozen
different countries but my specialty was
the Middle East my bachelor's degree was
in Middle Eastern studies and the CIA
taught me to speak Arabic fluently and
so
um my first overseas assignment was
uh
was working with Equity royal family
during the Iraqi occupation of Kuwait so
I was with them in Saudi Arabia I went
into Kuwait with the Marines on
Liberation day
and um and served there that I spent two
years in Bahrain went back to
headquarters to work on Iraq and then I
got bored about seven years into it like
very bored
and so I did something that was very
very unusual I I switched from analysis
to counter-terrorism operations and
worked uh then at the cia's
counter-terrorism center so then I
served in Athens for two years I served
as the the chief of counterterrorism
operations in Pakistan after 9 11 and
then I um finished up my career
at the United Nations in New York
wow incredible I 70 countries
wow that's did you have time to even
like explore or was it work 24th of it
oh I always made time to explore which
used to drive my colleagues crazy you
know if you're going to be for example
if you're going to be in Damascus
and you don't know if you'll ever be in
Damascus again then for God's sake take
a day hire a private tour guide and go
see all the stuff that you should see in
Damascus you know otherwise you know I I
knew guys I knew guys who would who
would never leave the hotel room except
to go to work
and then they'd go back to the hotel I'm
like are you crazy
so yeah you know every country has
weekends right everybody wants to be off
for the weekend so if you happen to find
yourself in some country you know let's
say you're in Jordan for the weekend
rent a car and drive to Petra
or if you're in Cairo go see the
pyramids or go on a safari or do
something
you can't just sit in a hotel every
Hotel looks exactly the same yeah
absolutely
um you know your your story is so
interesting I think one of the the
things that really stood out to me while
while first hearing about your story and
doing initial um additional research is
I didn't and maybe I'm the only one but
I didn't know that
the CIA allowed people lack of a better
term
um with them to go on news channels I
didn't know that happened no they don't
ever
right unless unless you're the director
uh yeah you can't
you can't be an activity active duty CI
officer and go on uh the news you can't
be an active duty CI officer and speak
to the media in any capacity unless
you're the director or deputy director
or in the office of um of public affairs
so you know that
oh
what what you were disclosing could
absolutely get you well first of all
fired and also imprisoned oh no no I was
never fired I left the CIA in 2000
foreign
and I went on ABC News in 2007 in
December of 2007. so I was already in
the private sector you know I knew it
was going to be controversial
but I didn't think it was going to be
life-altering and I'll tell you what it
shouldn't have been life-altering
because well for a couple of reasons
first
it's actually illegal in this country to
classify a crime
if something is a criminal act like
torture it is illegal to classify the
program for the purpose of keeping the
information from the American people
I believed then I believe now that the
torture program was a crime not just a
crime
in the United States as a violation of
the federal torture Act of 1946 or even
internationally as a violation of the
United Nations
um conventions Against torture but it
was a war crime and a crime against
humanity
and so it was clear to me that this
program was illegal I waited for five
years five and a half
for somebody to come out and say
something and nobody did
and so finally I did in December of
2007. now as you might imagine the CIA
the very next day filed what's called a
crimes report against me with the FBI
saying that I had um disclosed
classified information the FBI
investigated me from December of 2007 to
December of 2008 and then determined
that I had not committed a crime
so
I mean I kind of knew that I was gonna I
was gonna win because I hadn't committed
a crime but
three weeks later
Barack Obama became president and
he brought John Brennan on as the deputy
National Security adviser for
um uh counterterrorism John and I always
hated each other and none asked uh
Attorney General Eric Holder to secretly
reopen the case against me
I had no idea that they had reopened the
case I had no idea that my phones were
tapped that my emails were being
intercepted that I was being followed by
teams of FBI agents and then finally
four years a little bit more than four
years after I blew the whistle I was
arrested and charged with five felonies
including three counts of Espionage now
I hadn't committed Espionage and they
eventually dropped those charges
but to make the whole thing go away I
had to take a plea to a to a lesser
charge
wow
they
um yeah
good question good question and there's
actually background to that so when I
was first
when I was first
um arrested
uh
they were seeking 45 years in prison
and I said I'm not going to do 45
minutes
I didn't do anything wrong and then
they came back it was on a Monday and
they said take a guilty plea to to uh
an Espionage charge and you do 10 years
I turned it down on Wednesday they came
down to eight years I turned it down and
on Friday all in the same week they came
down to five years my lead attorney
was the legendary Plato Contreras and he
said
that he had been an attorney in
Washington DC for 52 years an attorney
for some of the biggest names in modern
American history
and he had never seen them come down in
time in their offers
and I said well why are they doing that
and very quickly he said to me because
they have a [__] case and they know it's
[__] we're going to trial and I said
okay we're going to trial
they waited like
I'm gonna say 10 more months and then
they came down to three and a half years
and I said no
and then they said all right best and
final officer or officer best and final
offer two and a half years you do 23
months
and I had until noon the next day to uh
to make the decision my wife and I
um now my ex-wife we stayed up all night
long talking about this and I decided to
turn it down I said naively as it turned
out that if if I just can get in front
of a jury they're going to see how
ridiculous this is and how punitive it
is and I'm gonna win because I hadn't
done anything wrong
so I emailed my lawyers and I said I'm
turning it down let's go to trial
they emailed me back I had 11 lawyers
three of them emailed me back saying
we're coming to the house so they came
to my house it was seven o'clock in the
morning very upset that I had decided to
turn this down and so one of them the
one who I actually liked and respected
the most
got right in my face like right in my
face and he said you know what your
problem is your problem is you think
this is about Justice and it's not about
Justice it's about mitigating damage
take the deal
so I said all right if I don't take the
deal and I'm found guilty what am I
realistically looking at and he said 12
to 18 years
and then he said listen I like you
you're a nice guy this could be a blip
in your life or it could be the defining
event in your life make it the blip
and so I took the deal now later on of
course I read studies and investigative
reports showing that the federal
government wins
98.2 percent of its cases
so so do you roll the dice knowing that
you have a 1.8 chance of winning I had
five kids
I couldn't take that chance
wow and wouldn't
um it would not have been a jury case oh
sure see and that's another thing I'm
glad you brought it up
my best friend's wife
has an uncle who happened to be O.J
Simpson's jury consultant
so as a favor
um he agreed to consult on my case so we
got him a security clearance through the
justice department he flew up to
Washington from Dallas he went through
15 000 pages of classified discovery
and I'll never forget the meeting that
we had with him and all the lawyers
together he said listen
if we were in any other District in
America I'd say let's go for it we're
going to win but the eastern district of
Virginia your jury is going to be made
up of people from or with relatives from
the CIA the FBI the Pentagon the
Department of Homeland Security and two
dozen intelligence and defense
contractors he said you don't have a
prayer
take the deal
and so I took the deal
absolutely what I mean
what it's it's so vague but what was
prison life did you have people in
prison who knew why you were in there
and thought you know what you're a
[__] traitor like how what was it
like the guards the guards were the only
ones who called me a traitor but they
had their heads up their asses anyway
um you know what what saved me
was there was one guy in the prison Mark
lanzelotti God bless him he's still one
of my best friends in the world Mark was
Italian I was gonna say it sure sounds
like it yeah Italian who was friends
with people who had last names like
Gambino and Luke Casey and banano and
Columbo
so
um mark
for whatever reason Mark followed my
case
and he saw four days before I arrived in
the New York Times that I was going to
be sent to the federal prison in Loreto
Pennsylvania and Mark took it on himself
to go to every single one of the
Italians and there were
say two dozen of them
and explain to them the difference
between an FBI agent and a CIA officer
FBI agents are cops and rats CIA
officers are overseas keeping us safe
from terrorists
and so when I arrived in shock because I
thought I was going to go to the minimum
security Work Camp and instead just to
screw me they put me in the actual
prison
which was two levels higher security
um the Italians welcomed me with open
arms
one of the things that I learned early
on and I wrote a book about this called
the Rel the um called doing time like a
spy how the CIA taught me to survive and
thrive in prison
um one of the things that I learned very
very early on just in the first couple
days is that prison is just a collection
of gangs
and you if you aren't in a gang and I
wasn't in a gang but um you have to
learn how to negotiate your way through
these gangs well I was sort of adopted
by the Italians and so
you know when word got around that I was
with the Italians
yeah I was I was in good shape
that's excellent
um one of our viewers uh vegan succubus
um we are Healthcare organizers and
activists and we were speaking earlier
um because I do
um you know me I've interviewed several
prisoners and and you know
um and they all have complaints about
how their health issues are ignored
things like that so I digress but how
how
you're not you're not digressing you're
not digressing this is a very very
important issue very important
um your health is going to worsen in
prison period there's almost nothing you
can do to stop that now if you go into
prison with pre-existing conditions
you're going to get worse in some cases
dramatically worse I went into prison
with
um with controlled Diabetes Type 2
diabetes I came out of prison with
uncontrolled type 2 diabetes 35 pounds
heavier and it's because you're given
this all carb all the time diet whether
you like it or not
and I'll give you some examples too
I wrote about this uh from prison and
and smuggled it out and Ariana
Huffington who at the time owned the
Huffington Post uh published it but um
my my first full day in prison was a was
a Friday and Friday's fish day
and one of the Italians said oh today's
Friday it's fish day and I said oh
that's good I like fish and he said
buddy you're not going to want to eat
this fish we call it
um sewer trout
and I said oh okay I'll stay away from
it well when I got down to the cafeteria
I saw these boxes that were stacked up
uh behind the uh the line and the uh the
the food line and the boxes were all
clearly marked they said Alaskan cod
Product of China
not for human consumption feed use only
and they were flopping it on everybody's
plates that was one incident another
incident was we
um every Wednesday was was taco night
and I'll tell you after two years of
these so-called tacos I've not been able
to force Mexican food down my throat
ever since and I mean like 10 years now
so it was the most disgusting
the most disgusting thing you can ever
imagine eating well one day we got an
all hands Memo from the warden saying
sorry everybody
but it turns out that the tacos we
served you six weeks ago
um were mismarked uh they were it was
marked ground beef it wasn't ground beef
it was dog food the mistake was made at
the meat packing plant it wasn't our
mistake they've been fined and the money
went to the National Treasury
okay disgusting but the shame is not
even that we were fed dog food
the shame is that we didn't even have
any idea that it was dog food because it
tastes the same as it did every single
Wednesday one other thing
um if you go to breakfast you have your
choice between
this lukewarm Brown water that they call
Coffee
or a glass of milk and lunch and dinner
you have a choice between water
and Kool-Aid
well people were I never touched the
Kool-Aid because I had diabetes but
people are drinking Kool-Aid Kool-Aid
Kool-Aid Kool-Aid and finally as the
level of the Kool-Aid is going down in
the tank
there's a dead rat at the bottom of the
Kool-Aid that people had been drinking
for days
and you know we're just one of 110
federal prisons across America
this happens everywhere it happens all
the time the food is not human grade
food
it's animal grade food
but it's cheap and so if if they're
trying to cut costs not just at the
federal level but
but at in state prisons and in local
jails
where do they cut costs they cut
food and they cut medication
that's how they save money and and then
because we've given ourselves this for
profit prison system they cut it that
much more you know there's a there's a
maximum security penitentiary here in
Virginia that's used as a transportation
point for both state and federal
prisoners called Red Onion uh prison and
um they haven't even had toilet seats in
10 years
because it it costs ten dollars to buy a
new toilet seat so why spend ten dollars
on a toilet seat when the company can
put it in their pockets
do you what do you think would change if
if and when we ever got rid of a
for-profit prisons how do you think that
would change the system as a whole
I think it might make prison Healthcare
slightly incrementally better
um which is great but it's not going to
cure anything what we need to do is
learn a lesson from some of our Western
European friends and allies
you know like like Germany and Norway
and Sweden where they know they know
that in order to reduce recidivism you
have to offer Education and Training
well we phased we phased out Education
and Training 1979.
and so you know time used to be when you
go to prison and you're like okay well I
can learn to be a plumber or an
electrician or to fix engines or or
something
and we don't do that at all anymore so
you know if you're a drug dealer
and you go to prison for two years or
five years or or 20 years
and you're not given any educational
training and you finally get out of
prison well what are you gonna do you're
gonna go right back to your neighborhood
and sell drugs because that's the only
thing you know how to do
and so nothing is going to change you
know why why did the Germans and the
Norwegians for example have recidivism
rates of about 15 percent and and ours
are 50 percent
they're the ones doing it right where
they put you not in a prison cell but in
a secure apartment
with a kitchen so you live like a human
being
you know and then go to school during
the day or learn your skill now we do
have this thing called uh
called prison Industries there was a
there was a prison industry uh I don't
even know what to call it a company at
my prison they made fiber optic cable
for for the U.S Navy
well you know what there's a private
company that makes fiber optic cable for
the US Navy but if the prison is paying
prisoners 10 cents an hour and the
company's paying their people 20 an hour
whose fiber optic cable is is the Navy
going to buy they're going to buy the
prison fiber optic cable but guess what
it's all degenerates and pedophiles and
drug dealers and and you know people
like this making the cable and they
don't give a [__] if the cable works or
not
it's not like what they're gonna get a
cut and pay from 10 cents an hour
and so these prison Industries Drive
legitimate businesses out of business
and then turn out substandard products
for companies to buy it's scandalous
right wow absolutely
um what are what are some of the things
you well I'm being presumptuous but what
are things that you learned while in
prison in in retrospects I'm I'm sure
you did a lot of analytical thinking and
um what are some of the things that you
really
um kind of focused on and feel like you
learned during that time well none of
it's good like I say I wrote this book
doing time like a spy what I found is
actually it's the same conclusion that
um
that uh
Professor Peter moshius uh of John Jay
College school of Criminal Justice wrote
about in his book in defense of flogging
which is a uh it not to be taken
literally the title he said that prisons
in America are really nothing more than
employment agencies for otherwise
unemployable
uneducated white men
there's a reason why almost all of the
country's prisons are in rural areas
it's because
uh there's no other industry there it's
just Farms or mines
and if you are
you know former military
and you couldn't make a go that
and you either flunked out of the little
local police academy or couldn't get
into the local police academy in the
first place
by God there's a spot for you in the
Bureau of Prisons
and so you get these guys I I met prison
guards who literally could not read they
couldn't even read
and and their barking orders at people
and they're abusive you know and one of
the other things that I learned was
almost to a man if you can get these
prison guards to start talking to you
they'll tell you essentially the same
story they're losers
who have nothing to do nothing that they
can do to make their lives better
um their parents or at least their dads
were prison guards in many cases their
grandfathers were prison guards and they
were bullied as children
and so now it's their turn now they're
gonna be the ones calling the shots
you know what there was one guard who
used to get in my face all the time and
finally I said to him dude you're gonna
spend way more time in this prison than
I ever am
you're the one that should be thinking
about changing your life
how do you dig that not well not no
you know they always try to be Joe tough
guy too I can't tell you how many times
they threaten me with solitary and I you
know I said to one of them
I have gone nose to nose with Al Qaeda
with Hezbollah with the Iranians and I'm
supposed to be afraid of you
please give me a little credit
and that's always back off
did you have to ever do solitary
uh no they never had the guts they never
had the I told them I have lived in far
worse places in the world than your
solitary unit not afraid of your
solitary besides I could lose I could
stand to lose a couple of pounds I I'm
not afraid of your solitary you know one
of the Italians was talking to a guard
he was one of the notorious guards he
was the only one that wore a stab vest
because he was afraid because he knew he
was such a dick he was afraid people
were going to try to stab him
so
the Italian said this guy went by the
name blue the nickname blue and he he
always covered up his real name with a
piece of masking tape
so um he said blue where are you gonna
be next quarter and blue said oh I'm
gonna be in um in the central one
housing unit and he said oh my friend
John's in central one blue says oh the
CIA guy I never mess with that guy and
the Italian laughed and said yeah why
not
and he said because that's all I need
he said I work my eight hour day and
then I go to my car and CNN's waiting
for me
and I said yeah exactly Jake Tapper came
to the prison to interview me I was on I
was on NPR three times I was in The
Economist and and Playboy and people and
Time Magazine and the cover of the Week
Magazine and
I wasn't afraid of those guys they were
afraid of me I actually
I actually uh filed a Freedom of
Information Act request on myself with
the Bureau of Prisons just to see out of
curiosity what it was that they had and
they sent me back 220 pages and 200
pages of it was just junk it was my my
medical records and my visitors list and
stuff like that but 20 Pages was clearly
marked at the top and the bottom in red
it was stamped foia exempt do not
release to inmate so either somebody was
so stupid at Bop headquarters or they
took pity on me
on purpose
but it was these memos that the that the
warden was sending out before I got
there warning the guards that I was
coming and the best memo it wasn't even
a memo it was just like like a flyer in
these big block letters it says caution
inmate has access to the media
and that really set the tone for the
whole 23 months
they would make their threats and then I
would make mine you know they would
threaten me and I'd say yeah well let's
see what Jake Tapper has to say about it
how about that why don't we give him a
call and see what he has to say and then
they would back off
did you have the ability to
um contact journalists or did you have
to wait till they contacted you no
that's a good question so the the Bureau
of Prisons regulations which I
familiarized myself with the moment I
arrived in prison were very very clear
that prisoners have unlimited access to
their attorneys and to the media it's
very very specific and in fact
even if you're in a Communications
management unit or in my case a modified
Communications management unit which is
supposed to restrict your access to the
outside world
all you have to do
um is on the envelope write legal mail
exempt from exempt exemption exempt from
inspection
or medium mail exempt from inspection
and so
journalists know this
right so they would write to me and put
on the envelope
um journalistic correspondence
and then I would respond and say
journalistic exemption media exemption
so yeah I was in close touch with with
journalists when I was in prison close
touch the New York Times came Scott
Shane from The New York Times uh Joby
Warwick from The Washington Post I told
you Jake Tapper from CNN came I gave
three interviews to NPR Ariana
Huffington came with two young
journalists so
I I was I was talking to the media a lot
of surprise places
CNN wanted to talk to you because you
considering
what you did
they're usually not very anti-war no
they're not they're very very mainstream
very neo-liberal neoconservative but but
Jake Tapper Jake Tapper was different
Jake Tapper even asked President Obama
in a in a press conference why he had
insisted on Prosecuting me when I
exposed a crime
and Obama just walked away from the
podium so Jake was different we've
actually stayed in touch since I since I
got home from prison he was one of those
guys that he he told me he just thought
it was wrong and so he wanted to reach
out and stay in touch
and and I got that I got that a lot I
got that from Scott chain at the New
York Times as well Scott wrote to me all
the time and then Joby Warwick both
before I went to prison and after I got
home
um said the same kind of thing
this is conjecture but do you think if
Obama was not elected that those charges
would have been brought
uh I do not John McCain uh got up on the
floor of the Senate six weeks before I
got out of prison and said that I had
provided the country with a great
national service and that the country
owed me a debt of gratitude and then I I
was home from prison only
a week or two and I got a call from a
guy from McCain's office saying
um Senator McCain wants to know how he
can be helpful
and I said well President Obama
confiscated my pension my federal
pension I had 20 years of proud you know
government service I really would like
my pension back and McCain
started the plan was to put an amendment
in the National Defense authorization
act and then he got brain cancer and
died so it never happened
but you know the funny thing is I'm a
lifelong Progressive I mean I I was a
third generation Democrat I'm no longer
a Democrat I think the Democrats are are
a war party the same as the Republicans
are so um so I'm independent like
independent independent same and um you
know so I I wasn't the natural uh McCain
voter I didn't vote for McCain and uh I
didn't vote for Obama either but uh but
McCain saw this for what it was it was a
cover-up and uh and he wanted help
wow that's pretty incredible
um you don't know when you're gonna
where you're gonna find allies you know
this is something that I've known for a
later in life you have to form strategic
alliances with people
with whom you might disagree uh you know
90 of the time I'll give you another
example
um I think that Fox News is um is the
channel the news channel of insanity
and I think that
ninety percent of the time Tucker
Carlson has views that are repulsive to
me
but by God Tucker Carlson is right on
this issue and Tucker Carlson is right
on Julian Assange and I've been on his
show a dozen times and he can't possibly
be more helpful to me than he has been
so you never know where you're going to
find allies
yeah absolutely
knows something that
I'm talking to their audiences too like
we don't have the same audiences so if
you're passionate about something
everyone should be exposed to it and
talking to people who agree with you all
the time is boring because and what are
you going to accomplish when you're just
talking to people who already agree with
you yeah that doesn't make any sense
yeah absolutely well I'm sure you know I
kind of like you know forgot the obvious
part let's talk about what you actually
disclosed
um and you did you were the first person
in the CIA to
um acknowledge that waterboarding was in
fact a thing
yes President Bush had
um
had said several things that were just
they were just bald-faced lies and I
knew he was lying
um he said that there was no torture
program
period
if there was torture he said it was the
result of a rogue CIA officer I knew
that that was just simply not true
and so
like I said you know I waited five and a
half years for somebody to come out and
say something and nobody did so I told
ABC News and the New York Times three
things I said that the CIA was torturing
its prisoners I said that torture was
official U.S government policy it was
not the result of a rogue and I said
that the policy had been personally
approved by the president himself
and so everything just kind of fell
apart from there
so they didn't um they took they took a
word they didn't ask for any kind of
tangibles whatsoever they just kind of
took you at your word do you or no well
no not really
um
I I wish that I could say that you know
I was the first person ever to utter
these words uh but I wasn't uh in the
two years before I I went public
the international Committee of the Red
Cross issued a report saying the CIA is
torturing people
uh Human Rights Watch came out with a
report saying the CIA is torturing
people and Amnesty International came
out with a report saying the CIA is
torturing people
and so I came out and I said they're
right the CIA is torturing people now
there was another whistleblower and
we've never learned who he or she is I
think I know who it is but I'm not going
to say
who went public before I did to say we
have a secret prison system that there
are prisons in a half a dozen different
countries around the world nobody is
supposed to know about it and they're so
secret that in many cases the leaders of
those countries don't know that there
are secret CIA prisons in their
countries these are handshake deals
between the head of the CIA and the head
of those countries intelligence services
and their own elected officials don't
know that they exist
so word was kind of already out there
that there's some bad [__] going down
seriously wow it's
kind of
regret not coming forward sooner well
yes all the time I I've thought about it
from the very beginning
I I should not have been as as careful
as I was now there was one mistake I
made it was it was a very big mistake I
should have hired an attorney before
blowing the whistle I should have had
that attorney sitting next to me when I
blew the whistle instead I I was forced
to be reactive and I I waited until I
blew the whistle the government fell on
my head and then I went out and got an
attorney that was a mistake and and I I
worn other whistleblowers or would-be
whistleblowers hire an attorney first
have the attorney sitting next to you
before you say anything so that was a
mistake but otherwise yeah I should have
done it sooner I wish I had done it
sooner
are there other things that you can
share publicly that that was going on
within the CIA
well there were several things that were
going on in the CIA that I believed were
all criminal activities and they and
they've all since been revealed uh of
course the obvious is the torture
program the the other thing is the
secret prison system but one thing that
that we really haven't had a national
discussion about is rendition and
extraordinary rendition there's a big
difference between the two rendition is
easy rendition is let's say you are from
Egypt I'm just making this up you're
from Egypt and so
I catch you in Pakistan a rendition is I
send you back to Egypt now
they're not going to be very nice to you
when you get back there right there
you're going to have a tough time you
may not survive that tough time
but they're going to do stuff that is
clearly illegal they're gonna they're
gonna attach electrodes to your genitals
they're gonna maybe rape your wife in
front of you they're going to do all
different kinds of things
an extraordinary rendition is
again let's say you're Egyptian and I
catch you in Pakistan an extraordinary
rendition is I don't send you back to
Egypt I send you to
Morocco or Israel
or you know
Indonesia and I don't tell
representatives of your government that
you're that I have you and that you're
in another country literally nobody
knows where you are nobody and you're
probably not going to survive that
either
that's an extraordinary rendition
wow and it
just yes but it's very very easy to make
mistakes we've made mistakes repeatedly
you know you you may have heard of the
case of uh Maher irar
Maher um was a uh political science
professor at the University of Toronto
and he he was originally Syrian he was a
naturalized Canadian Citizen and in the
summer of 2001 he went to Syria to visit
relatives and he was there for about
three months he was there through 9 11.
and then um
and then
he was flying back to Toronto well his
flight like most flights most
international flights going into Canada
stop at JFK in New York
so
the FBI pulled him off that flight and
they turned him over to the CIA and the
CIA
sent him back to Syria
and told the syrians
that
this guy's Al Qaeda we want you to
tenderize him a little bit
well in the meantime his wife is waiting
for him at the airport in Toronto and he
never gets off the plane
so she calls the airline and the airline
said oh he never got on the flight well
a month passes and he's just missing
nobody's heard from him and she gets a
credit card bill and it turns out that
he bought a pair of sunglasses
through duty-free on the plane you know
how they come and say duty free
duty-free anybody he bought a pair of
sunglasses and it appealed it appeared
on the credit card bill
so then she went to the Canadian
government and she said he was on that
flight
he landed in New York and then
disappeared
well then the Canadians went to the CIA
and they went to the FBI and
well after nine months after he had
undergone merciless torture at the hands
of the Syrian intelligence service the
syrians came back to us and said listen
we think this is the wrong guy
there's another guy
with a similar name
but it's not Mahar arar
and they let him go
well
he finally makes his way back to Canada
he sues the U.S government in the
eastern district of Virginia here where
I live and the CIA goes to court and
says your honor we can't defend this
suit National Security we would have to
reveal classified information uh request
that you dismiss the suit the judge says
dismissed National Security
and that was it
so he sued the Canadian government
because they did nothing to stop the CIA
from snatching him they did nothing to
help their own Citizen and he won a six
million dollar settlement
but I spoke to him recently and he told
me that he has such severe PTSD from
this episode that he hasn't left his
house in 10 years
he's just unable to function
you know there's another guy by the name
of of Khalid al-masri
German citizen he had originally been
Egyptian and um he was a green Grocer in
uh in Germany in Munich I think it was
and one night he had a fight with his
wife their marriage was not good he had
a fight with his wife and he said I
gotta get out of here
well he had a brother in Macedonia and
so he gets on a bus
he's got this ticket to Macedonia and
he's going to go visit his brother well
the CIA intercepts a message that
somebody named Khaled al-masri intends
to blow up the American Embassy in
Tirana Albania now Khalid is like John
of the Middle East
righty just means the Egyptian it
doesn't it's not even really a name it
just means Khalid the Egyptian so there
are like 10 million people with the name
Khalid al-masri so
the CI is like oh my God this guy he's
gonna blow up the American Embassy in
Toronto and then they see wait a minute
is on a bus and he's heading in the
direction of Albania
so we go to the Serbian intelligence
service and we say get this guy off this
bus
and they stopped the bus in the middle
of nowhere they take Khaled Al Messi off
the bus they turn him over to the CIA
the CIA sends him to Egypt and we tell
the Egyptian this guy's Al Qaeda he's
going to blow up our Embassy so go ahead
and do what you guys do best
well
a year and a half later
the Egyptians come to us and say we
think this is the wrong guy
it's a really common name this guy
doesn't know anything he's a green
grocer well by the time they released
him with torture scars all over his body
he had a beard down to his waist he's
clutching a copy of the Quran and all he
wants to talk about is killing Americans
so that's the problem with the
extraordinary rendition program it's a
war crime
wow so in other words and and I've heard
other people say this as well you you
believe that you know new members of of
things like Al Qaeda are created by
people who are presumed part of them
oh without a doubt you know I I can't
tell you I I was responsible for the
capture of dozens and dozens of Al Qaeda
Fighters
legitimate Al-Qaeda Fighters
most of them were not what you would
expect most of them were 18 or 19 years
old
crying through the entire interrogation
asking if they could call their mom
right
and
they had no beef with the United States
until we bombed their Village
until we sent a drone that killed their
cousin or killed their dad or killed
their sister and then they wanted to
make Jihad Against The Americans
sure
wow happens all the time
right
wow um what are some of you know the
things that you learned being an
intelligent officer that you have taken
to apply
um in in life as of now oh yeah
that's a great question the most
important lesson is education education
education
and economic development listen every
one of these guys told exactly the same
story they were from some isolated
Village in their country
um most of them were illiterate
um they they wanted to get married but
what man would want his daughter to
marry some uneducated guy with with no
uh you know no job prospects I wouldn't
want my daughter to marry some
uneducated illiterate jobless homeless
guy
and so the local Imam
told them what are you doing here in
this Village you should go to
Afghanistan to make Jihad against the
Americans because we'll pay you 500 a
month and if you're martyred we'll give
your your parents a 500 martyrdom bonus
you don't want to stay here and then
when you come home you'll be a hero and
then you can get a wife
and they were like well I got nothing
else going for me I might as well just
go make Jihad Against The Americans
and then John caught them in some safe
house someplace in Pakistan
so you know one of the things I learned
was
if we were spending money and I don't
mean to sound like some air-headed you
know peace Nick I mean this sincerely if
we would spend some of the money that we
spend on you know so-called defense
which is really offense on things like
like International education programs
and economic development
digging water wells or building
electrical grids or something to put
these people to work and put them
through school
then maybe we wouldn't have all these
problems with terrorism
and you know it's it's humorous when you
were describing how they
um lack of a better term get people to
join Al Qaeda it kind of sounds like the
same process as the Army honestly it
that it's exactly the same process as
the Army and I'll go on further it's
exactly the same process as the Bureau
of Prisons
you know uh what do you want to do here
if you want to stay in this isolated
stupid Village in the middle of nowhere
then at least you should come work for
the prison you can beat people up and
hit them with your stick and kick them
and send them into little cages and
solitary confinement and if the
prisoners are women you can rape them
and nobody's gonna rat you out
come on we'll have a lot of fun it's the
same idea
wow absolutely well I I can't believe
it's been an hour already this is I I
feel like I could talk to you forever oh
and I'm supposed to tell you
um by one of my friends we are in
Pennsylvania as well so she's that
you're a Pennsylvania yeah yeah I am New
Castle PA where are you located
I'm in Harrisburg oh okay not far I was
in FCI Loreto which is halfway between
Altoona and Johnstown right right that's
awesome we don't get as many uh pencil
tuckians that are uh that that awesome
I'll tell you one funny thing somebody
just for fun during covid on uh on
Facebook they they made this post
um uh say something about yourself that
is controversial and is generally not
cool you know something like that and I
wrote All right I'll admit I am
prejudiced against Amish people
I am I admit it I grew up in a heavily
Amish county and they're just not very
nice people
[Music]
I know I'm by Lancaster I know I get it
you know I get it
um yeah I mean
that's true that is very true
um
something you would like the uh viewers
to take away from this interview oh
thank you for that
um I would like them to take away
something that I learned ex post facto
uh and that is that you know at the CIA
and not just at the CIA but in many
organizations and at many points in life
our culture our society wants us to
believe that
that life is a shade of gray or it's
Many Shades of Gray
and in many cases that's just simply not
true some things are black and white
they are right and wrong
at the CIA they're not going to teach
you
morals they're not going to teach you
ethics you have to go in with your own
personal uh set of ethics and you have
to
acknowledge that some things are black
and white they're either right or wrong
and if something is wrong you've got to
say something you've got to say
something nobody ever wants to be the
first be the first
it's worth it your children will respect
you and you'll be able to sleep at night
absolutely and
and um is something about Assange I know
you're a huge supporter and especially
everything you've gone through I know it
upsets us but I can't even fathom
um what it does to you to see what is
happening to this man right now
um so yeah do you want to speak a little
on on why you're passionate about
Assange and
this case against Julian Assange is a
very very slippery slope whether you
like Julian or not whether you agree
with Julian or not you have to
acknowledge that he is a journalist and
even if you don't agree that he's a
journalist you have to agree that he's a
publisher right he exposed war crimes
well if Julian Assange as a publisher is
prosecuted for Espionage for doing his
job and for for exposing war crimes to
the American people
then every journalist in America is
going to be subject to an Espionage Act
prosecution for doing his or her job
that is not what our founding fathers
envisioned it's not what the
Constitution tells us so we have to
stand up for him let me add one other
thing about Julian Assange when Julian
first was incarcerated at belmarsh
prison which is a maximum security
penitentiary in South London
he would write me letters and he would
say
do me a favor call this lawyer and tell
him that call this other lawyer and tell
him this call this guy and tell him I
need an article about that and it was
just a list of things to do
the last letter I got from Julian
was one sentence long and all it said
was please pray for me
they have broken him
to the point where I'm not sure that he
can survive this
so we've got to be militant
in our determination to help Julian
Assange not just for Julian but for the
Constitution's First Amendment
absolutely wow that's heartbreaking and
please also we all need to stand by
Stella give her our support
um she's talked about the boys the other
day and it was just absolutely
heartbreaking it's heartbreaking it is
yes I mean that's a whole another hour
conversation about what the CIA did to
him in the in the Ecuadorian Embassy and
this nonsense he's held he's held in
solitary confinement in belmarsh maximum
security for the last three and a half
years on a bail jumping charge
it's just outrageous
absolutely awful yeah we definitely uh
solidarity with Julian all the way
um and and also um why don't you give
where people can find you and also be
exciting
um Assange event coming up thank you Joy
um I'm on sub stack uh John kiriaku my
full name I'm also on Twitter and
Facebook uh but substack is where I try
to put everything I just got back from
Cuba a couple of days ago and I I've
written a series about what uh how U.S
policy is screwing the Cuban people to
um
on Sunday this Sunday in Washington is a
big event an anti-war event that just by
virtue of of Word of Mouth I think is
going to be a very very big deal and
then we had something called the
belmarsh tribunal a few weeks ago uh
about Julian Assange it was held at the
national Press Club there's going to be
a mirror event in Sydney Australia on
the
first of March or 2nd of March something
like that anyway big big event in in
March
follow uh follow Stella uh Morris on on
Twitter and Facebook she she has all the
latest from Julian and um and take to
the streets
absolutely that is so exciting I'm
looking forward to all your posts about
that
um in Australia as well that's so
exciting
um John I cannot thank you enough you've
been on my like future top five lists
for like over a year
no I I appreciate the invitation very
much thanks for having me absolutely
absolutely and thank you guys so much
for watching
um smash the like button smash subscribe
um so thank you guys so much uh tune in
Monday for another uh postmortem
breakdown and much love to everyone
thanks again John thank you
thanks everybody
bye-bye